Floyd Bass Collection of John E. Rogers 1994.0076
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Floyd Bass Collection of John E. Rogers
undated, 1904-1982
1994.0076
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
1.0 Linear feet
The collection contains clippings, sound recordings, books, an honorary degree, and research posters relating to Dr. John E. Rogers.
Biography
As a youth Rogers attended Weaver High School, where he was the first black student to be elected captain of the football team. He retired in 1968 after 40 years with the U.S. Postal Service. The first black to land a job with the Hartford post office, Rogers' last post was postmaster of the Bishops Corner, West Hartford, office. He was awarded an honorary doctorate in humane letters in 1970 from the University of Hartford and taught the first black history course at the University of Hartford.
In 1976, Rogers wrote the Inner City Bicentennial Booklet, which told the achievements of blacks during the 1700s, and was distributed to Connecticut inner city youngsters. He was the recipient of many awards, most notably the first St. Benedict Award from the Catholic Interracial Council of Hartford, the Charter Oak Leadership Medal of the Greater Hartford Chamber of Commerce, and the Thurgood Marshall Award fo the NAACP. Dr. Rogers served on the boards of of many civic organizations, including the Community Renewal Team of Greater Hartford, the Urban League and the Hartford Neighborhood Center.
The Dr. John E. Rogers Memorial Library was opened on Main Street in Hartford in 1977, the same year that Rogers was named to the Freedom of Information Commission by Gov. Ella T. Grasso. He served until ill health forced him to resign in 1981. Dr Rogers passed away on Friday, May 28, 1982 at the age of 75.
Dr. Floyd Bass, professor in the UConn School of Education, was appointed as the research assistant for the Center for Black Studies, the predecessor of the Institute for African American Studies. Launched in June 1969, the Center was established as the result of a committee of faculty, administrators and students proposal. The committee requested an operating budget to cover colloquia, travel, temporary assistance, research assistants, library acquisition and printing. A personnel budget covered permanent positions for a director, secretary and five positions for newly hired Black faculty members. Dr. Bass was assigned as the Center's Research Assistant in accordance with a pilot plan for attracting Black scholars to the University. By 1976, Dr. Bass had been appointed director of the Center.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains framed clippings, a framed novelty song collection, a framed book collection, a framed honorary degree, and research posters.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Provenance and Acquisition
Provenance is unknown, although it is presumed that the materials were donated after the materials were exhibited on campus.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to various aspects of Connecticut history and the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Separated Materials
The following titles have been catalogued:
Narrative of Henry Watson, a fugitive slave. Dodd
Manual of the Congregational Church, in Bolton, Conn. Dodd
The experience of Thomas H. Jones, who was a slave for forty-three years. Dodd
Experience and personal narrative of Uncle Tom Jones; who was for forty years a slave. Dodd
In Memoriam. Professor Wiley Lane of the Howard University, Washington, D.C. Dodd
The Life of James Williams, better known as Professor Jim, for half a century janitor of Trinity College. Dodd
Bass, Floyd; Clippings (information artifacts).; Photographs.; Publications.
- Series I: Rogers Collection, Bulk, 1975-1982; undated, 1904-1982
  African Americans--Education (Higher)--Connecticut.; African Americans--Study and teaching--Connecticut.
  - Citations, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, undated, 1968-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Content Note
    [Subjects include: John Roger's achievements between 1968 - 1970.]
    African Americans--Newspapers.; African Americans--Study and teaching--Connecticut.
  - Great American Achievement Program (booklet), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    [Subjects include: evolution of African American portrayal in music from 1904 - 1964.]
    African Americans--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; Racism—United States.
  - Inner City Bicentennial Booklet, 1776-1976, 1975; This frame exhibits several books from 1848 - 1876. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    African Americans--Study and teaching--Connecticut.
  - Photographs, 1970, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sheet music, undated, 1904-1954; These posters portray African- American involvement in the American Revolutionary war. African American poetry is also highlighted in this collection.
    African Americans--Education (Higher)--Connecticut.; African Americans--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; American Revolution Bicentennial, 1776-1976—Connecticut.
    - Brown Skin! The "Singing-one-step,", 1916 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - By the Watermelon Vine, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Fats" Waller's original piano conceptions, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Nat "King" Cole song album of recorded hits, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Sam, the accordion man, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 10)